Guide to the Frances Campbell Brown Papers, 1932-1975
Duke University. University Archives
Frances Campbell Brown papers 1932-1975
Duke University. University Archives
Frances Campbell Brown, 1906-
9.0 linear feet Extent: 6000 Items
Frances Campbell Brown was a professor of chemistry at Duke from approximately 1931-1973, and a professor emeriti after 1973. Professor Brown was also active in the American Association of University Professors (AAUP), serving as its second vice president from 1964-1966. This collection contains correspondence, subject files, committee minutes, printed matter, speeches, and reports concerning personal, professional, departmental, university matters as well as the American Association of University Professors (AAUP). The bulk of the material dates from 1958-1968.
All materials relating to the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) and Committee A are restricted until 2017.
UA.29.02.0221
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request. All materials relating to the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) and Committee A are restricted until 2017.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Frances Campbell Brown Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer starting in 1969.
Biographical Note
Frances Campbell Brown, educator and chemist, was born in Johnson, Tennessee. She received her bachelor's degree from Agnes Scott in 1928 and her Ph.D from Johns Hopkins in 1931. Brown was a professor of chemistry at Duke from approximately 1931-1973, and a professor emeriti after 1973. Professor Brown was also active in the American Association of University Professors (AAUP), serving as its second vice president from 1964-1966. She was also active in the Duke AAUP chapter, and served on the Undergraduate Faculty Council Committee on Program II and a number of other university and departmental committees.
Collection Overview
This collection contains correspondence and subject files concerning personal, professional, departmental, and university matters; the bulk of the material dates from 1958-1968. Documents include letters, memoranda, committee minutes, printed matter, speeches, and reports. There is a small amount of material concerning the 1962 revision of the University Bylaws in light of the American Association of University Professor's (AAUP) statements on tenure. Major subjects in the collection include academic freedom and tenure, the AAUP, faculty responsibility for educational policy, science libraries, the Department of Chemistry, admissions and Program II. The bulk of the material was generated or received by Dr. Brown in her role as a member and officer of the AAUP.
All materials regarding the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) and Committee A are restricted until 2017.
Subject Headings
American Association of University Professors; Duke University -- Admission; Duke University. Dept. of Chemistry; Women in science
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, 1932-1975, 9.0 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
  All materials relating to the American Association of University Professors (AAUP) and Committee A are restricted until 2017.
  - Frances Campbell Brown, Personal Papers (Box 1)
  - Committee G - American Association of University Professors (Box 1)
  - Committee on Tenure Practices and Hearings (Box 1)
  - Agenda Committee, Atlanta, April 1966 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors Executive Committee (Box 1)
  - Nominating Committees - American Association of University Professors, May 24-25, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions - American Association of University Professors, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting, April 9-10, 1965 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors Meeting, Atlanta, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Committee A Handbook (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors Committee A, October 1960 (Box 1)
  - Committee A, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Committee A, October 24, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Report of Committee A Procedures, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Committee A, St. Louis Meeting, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Committee A, June - November 1964 (Box 1)
  - Committee A, April 1965 (Box 1)
  - Committee A, October 1965 (Box 1)
  - Committee A, Atlanta, April 1966 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Academic Freedom and Retirement (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors Council Meeting, November 7-8, 1958 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors Council Meeting, April 1958 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors, November 6-7, 1959 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors Council, April 1960 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors Council Meeting, October 1960 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors Council, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Council Meeting, Boston, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Council Meeting, St. Louis, April 1964 (Box 2)
  - Council, October 1964 (Box 2)
  - Council, April 8, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Council Meeting, October 29-30, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Council Meeting, Atlanta, April 1966 (Box 2)
  - Davis, Bertram H. - American Association of University Professors General Secretary - Washington D.C. (Box 2)
  - Educom (Box 2)
  - I.A.U.P.L. (Box 2)
  - UNESCO, New Orleans, La., September 18-20, 1966 (Box 2)
  - American Association of University Professors Mississippi Study (Box 2)
  - Michigan Community Colleges Collective Bargaining (Box 2)
  - Assorted Files/Clippings, mostly concerned with Mississippi (Box 2)
  - Silver and University of Mississippi (Box 2)
  - Mississippi Report, July 26, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Mississippi Interviews (Box 2)
  - University of Mississippi (Box 2)
  - Mississippi (Box 2)
  - University of Arizona (Box 2)
  - Arizona, Committee A, April 1965 (Box 2)
  - Fisk University (Box 2)
  - Monmouth College (Box 2)
  - University of Miami Medical School (Box 2)
  - Committee A - American Association of University Professors, Wyly Case (Box 2)
  - C.W. Post College, Sittler case (Box 2)
  - St. John's University (Box 2)
  - Tufts University (Box 2)
  - Gonzaga University (Box 2)
  - Montana State (Box 2)
  - South Dakota (Box 2)
  - New Mexico (Box 2)
  - Illinois (Box 2)
  - Auburn (Box 2)
  - Alcorn and Miss. Vocational College (Box 2)
  - Tougaloo College (Box 2)
  - Central Missouri State College (Box 2)
  - Columbia Union College (Box 2)
  - Emporia College, Kansas (Box 2)
  - Westminster College, Pa. (Box 2)
  - Nebraska State Teachers College (Box 3)
  - Alcorn A&M College and Alabama State College (Box 3)
  - American University of Beirut (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 3)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 3)
  - AAU, 1964 (Box 3)
  - American Association of University Professors Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Reprints on Disclaimer Affidavit, 1958-1961 (Box 3)
  - Board-Administration-Faculty / AGB-ACE-American Association of University Professors (Box 3)
  - Meiklejohn Award, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Sponsored Research - Conflict of Interest (Box 3)
  - Assorted "unfiled" papers (Box 3)
  - Assorted "unfiled" papers (#2) (Box 3)
  - Retirement and Academic Freedom - Preparation of Questionnaire (Box 3)
  - Questionnaire Returns - Retirement and Academic Freedom (Box 3)
  - American Association of University Professors Retirement Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Association Procedures on Investigation - Regulations on Academic Freedom and Tenure (Box 3)
  - Lincoln College (Illinois) (Box 3)
  - Princeton University (Box 3)
  - First Draft of Paper for September 13, 1967 (Box 3)
  - ACS Talk, Chicago, September 13, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Collective Bargaining, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Speaker Ban (Box 3)
  - American Association of University Professors NC State Conference (Box 3)
  - American Association of University Professors State and Regional Conferences, except North Carolina (Box 4)
  - American Association of University Professors Duke Chapter (Box 4)
  - American Association of University Professors San Francisco Meeting, 1963 (Box 4)
  - North Central College (Box 4)
  - George Washington—Reichard (Box 4)
  - Higgins’ Case—Arkansas State Teacher’s (Box 4)
  - American Association of University Professors Annual Meeting, 1962 (Box 4)
  - American Association of University Professors Resolutions Committee, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Monmouth (Box 4)
  - Committee A, 1963 (Box 4)
  - A.M. & N. College of Arkansas (Box 4)
  - University of South Florida (Box 4)
  - University of Florida—Act 10 (Box 4)
  - Mercy College (Box 4)
  - Northwestern University—Wyly (Box 4)
  - Grove City College (Box 4)
  - Sam Houston State Teacher's College (Box 4)
  - Committee A, April 1962 (Box 4)
  - College of the Ozarks (Box 4)
  - University of Illinois—Professor Koch (Box 4)
  - Carolinas-Virginia Academic Freedom Seminar: Student Involvement in Extra Campus Affairs, Session 3, February 24-26, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Watt, Vance (Correspondence between Frances Brown and Vance Watt, Brookwood School) (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Dr. Neil Campbell, University of Edinburgh, 1939-1942 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Dr. Neil Campbell, University of Edinburgh, 1943-1970 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (folder 2) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-June 1965 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, July-Dec. 1965 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1965, (folder 2) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1965, (folder 4) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966, (folder 2) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966, (folder 8) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1967, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1968, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, July-Dec. 1969 (Box 5)
  - Search committee for Chaplain, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Gross (Paul M.) portrait, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Paul M. Gross Symposium, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - The Chemistry Library: Its Location and Administration, 1963-1968 (Box 6)
  - Bylaws, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Letter to (Chemistry) Alumni, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Dedication of Paul M. Gross Building, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Program II, 1969-1972, (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - John Saylor Memorial Fund, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Committee S—Duke, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - American Association of University Professors talk at High Point College, 1958-1960 (Box 6)
  - American Association of University Professors talk at Greensboro, 1963 (Box 6)
  - American Association of University Professors talk at Kentucky State Conference, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Talk at Appalachian State Teachers College, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Talk at St. Andrews, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Committee on faculty qualifications and improvement, 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - Admissions (Committee on Undergraduate), 1967-1969 (Box 6)
  - Majors committee (Chemistry Dept.), 1968-1969 (Box 6)
  - ACLU, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Department awards committee, 1967-1968 (Box 6)
  - Graduation with distinction—chemistry, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - Printed Matter—Reprints, 1950-1963 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 6)